Register to the Wagner-Jenkins Correspondence
Yale University Music Library
Wagner-Jenkins Correspondence
1874-1891
Misc. Ms. 345
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Correspondence between the families of Richard Wagner and Newell Sill Jenkins.
Jenkins, N. S. (Newell Sill)
Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883
Wagner, Cosima, 1837-1930
Wagner, Siegfried, 1869-1930
Wagner family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Newell Jenkins (grandson of Newell Sill Jenkins) in 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Newell Sill Jenkins (1840-1919) was an American dentist who spent most of his career in Europe, practicing chiefly in Dresden. He had many notable patients, including the composer Richard Wagner and his family. The Wagner family and the Jenkins family became friends, and they exchanged many letters. For more information about Dr. Jenkins, see John M. Hyson, Jr., "Dr. Newell Sill Jenkins: Progenitor of Cosmetic Dentistry," Journal of the California Dental Association, Vol. 31, No. 8, August, 2003, pp. 626-629. Dr. Jenkins was the grandfather of the American conductor Newell Jenkins (1915-1996).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists chiefly of correspondence between the families of the composer Richard Wagner and Dr. Newell Sill Jenkins. The Wagner family is represented by letters from Richard Wagner, his wife Cosima, and their children Siegfried and Eva, as well as Daniela von Bülow (Cosima's daughter by her previous marriage to Hans von Bülow). Only two of the letters are by Richard Wagner, but they are of particular interest; both dated 1880, they discuss his interest in visiting the United States or even moving there permanently, explaining that he would require a million dollars to do so. Jenkins tried to support Wagner's schemes, but they never came to fruition.
The original letters are accompanied by typed transcriptions, as well as English translations of the German-language letters. The collection also includes two Bayreuth performance schedules and two 20th-century articles.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence. II. Miscellaneous printed material.
Composers -- Germany -- Correspondence; Jenkins, Newell -- Gift, 1986
- Correspondence, 1874-1891; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically, with undated items filed at the end.
  - Inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From C. Wagner to Dr. Jenkins, 1874 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General
    Bayreuth
  - From Cosima Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1877 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From C. Wagner to Mrs. Jenkins, 1879 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Wahnfried
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1879 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    [Walpurgisstrasse, Dresden]
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1879 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Richard Wagner [to N.S. Jenkins], 1880 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    "Rec'd Dresden Febry. 12 1880."
  - From N.S. Jenkins to [Richard Wagner], 1880 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Dresden
  - From [N.S. Jenkins] to A.D. White, 1880 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From Richard Wagner and C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1880 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Naples
  - Draft of a letter from [N.S. Jenkins] to Wagner, No date [after 1880 July 13] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From Kingsley Twining to Dr. Jenkins, 1880 July 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Oneida County, New York
  - From J.S. Dwight to Dr. N.S. Jenkins, 1880 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From Newell Sill Jenkins to Mr. J.R. Folsom, 1880 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1880 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - From B.J. Lang to Richard Wagner, [1880] August 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Boston
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1880 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Siena
  - From N.S. Jenkins to Madame Wagner, 1880 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Paris
  - From J.S. Dwight to Dr. N.S. Jenkins, 1880 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1880 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - From F.S.D [Davenport] to "Doc" [N.S. Jenkins], 1880 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Bangor
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1880 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Venice
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1880 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1881 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Palermo
  - From Joe to "Doc" [N.S. Jenkins], 1881 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    New York
  - Card enclosed with Christmas gift to Mr. and Mrs. Jenkins, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From Daniela v. Bülow to [N.S. Jenkins], 1882 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From C. Wagner to Mrs. Jenkins, 1882 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From Siegfried Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1882 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From Siegfried [Wagner] to Dr. Jenkins, 1883 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From Daniela v. Bülow to Dr. Jenkins, 1884 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From Carrie Pringle to Mr. Jenkins, 1886 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    London
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1888 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From C. Wagner to Mr. Jenkins, 1889 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From C. Wagner to Mrs. Jenkins, 1889 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From Eva Wagner to Dr. Jenkins, 1891 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From Siegfried Wagner to Dr. Jenkins, No date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - From "Deinem Judenhasser" to Leo [Jenkins], No date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Card from Frau Wagner to Mrs. Jenkins, No date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Calling card; "Frau Wagner/geb Liszt" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Calling card of Richard Wagner (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous printed material, Series II
  - Bühnenfestspiele in Bayreuth., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Calendar of performances.
  - [Bühnenfestspiele in Bayreuth], 1889 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Calendar of rehearsals and performances. The opera house and date are not named in this fragment, but it appears to be for the Bayreuth Festival in 1889.
  - Klaus Liepman, "Wagner's Proposal to America," High Fidelity, December 1975, pp. 70-72. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bernard Levin, "The Unspeakable Wagners,"Times [of London], 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)